Finding Aid for Logic of Computers Group (University of Michigan) records, 1950-1979
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Logic of Computers Group (University of Michigan) Records 1950-1979
University of Michigan. Logic of Computers Group.
13 linear feet
87180 Bimu C565 2
Interdepartmental University of Michigan faculty group formed in 1956 and headed by Arthur Burks to investigate the use of computers in communication. Records include correspondence, project reports, grant proposals and some personal papers of Arthur Burks.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were donated by Arthur M. Burks in October 1984 and 1986. Donor No. 7118
The record group is open without restriction.
The Logic of Computers Group (LoCG) at the University of Michigan was established in 1956 as an informal group of faculty members from various departments who were interested in studying the logical formalisms related to computers and natural systems. The group was directed by philosophy professor Arthur Burks and early an worked out Of the Operations Research Department of the Engineering Research Institute. In 1957, Burks and Gordon Peterson, of the Phonetics Laboratory in the Department of Speech, petitioned the graduate school, and along with five other professors were constituted a committee with power to award advanced graduate degrees in "Communications Sciences." The program was chaired by Peterson until it achieved departmental status in 1965. After a year under an interim chairman, Burks chaired the "Computer and Communications Sciences" Department until 1971. The LoCG was an important component of both the early program and, later, the department. Although it worked out of its own computing center and was funded entirely by grants from governmental agencies, it provided the department with faculty expertise and produced a large percentage of the departmental PhDs.
The Logic of Computers Group records (12 linear feet)document some of the earliest use of and research on computing on the University of Michigan campus. The records are divided into six series: CONCOMP; Correspondence; Grants and Proposals; Papers and Reports; Arthur Burks Personal files; and Photographs.
Subjects:
Computers.; Burks, Arthur W. (Arthur Walter), 1915-2008.; University of Michigan. Logic of Computers Group.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
University of Michigan. Logic of Computers Group.; Computers.; Burks, Arthur W. (Arthur Walter), 1915-2008.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- CONCOMP (conversational uses of computers)
  The University of Michigan CONCOMP project involved research in the conversational use of Computers and was supported by the Department of Defense. The files here (one linear foot) consist almost entirely of published "Technical Reports" and, "Memoranda" that resulted from the research. The reports are arranged alphabetically by the last name of the author. It is uncertain how many of the authors were members of the LoCG.
  - General (Box 1)
  - Reports
    - Progress (Box 1)
    - A-B (Box 1)
    - C-H (Box 1)
    - I-L (Box 1)
    - M (Box 1)
    - P-S (Box 1)
    - T-Z (Box 2)
- Correspondence
  The correspondence files (one linear foot) are from the years 1961-1963 and 1968-1979. They are arranged chronologically and consist of outgoing correspondence by members of the LoCG.
  - 1961 (Box 2)
  - 1962 (Box 2)
  - 1963 (Box 2)
  - 1968 (Box 2)
  - 1969 (Box 2)
  - 1970 (Box 2)
  - 1971 (Box 2)
  - 1972 (Box 2)
  - 1973 (Box 2)
  - 1974 (Box 2)
  - 1975-1976 (Box 2)
  - 1977-1979 (Box 2)
  - 1958-1964 A-2 (Box 12)
  - 1960 (Box 12)
  - 1964 (Box 12)
  - 1965-June 1966 (Box 12)
  - July-December 1966 (Box 12)
  - 1967 (Box 12)
- Grants and Proposals
  The Grants and Proposals files (two and one half linear feet) contain correspondence, memos, and proposal drafts. They are arranged alphabetically by agency to which the proposals were directed and grants received from. Within agency, the files are arranged alphabetically by last name of the University of Michigan project leader or proposal originator (the majority of whom are Burks) and thereafter, alphabetically by project title.
  - Air Force
    - Burks, Arthur "Logical Design of Automata," 1958 (Box 3)
    - Holland, John "Proposal for Research on The Behavior of Delayed-Feedback Systems," 1957 (Box 3)
    - Burks and Holland "Research In Theory of Adaptive Systems," 1963-1965 (Box 3)
  - Army
    - Burks, Arthur
      - "An Algebra for Automata," 1957-1960 (Box 3)
      - "Application of Mathematics to Automata," 1960 (Box 3)
      - "Languages and Automata," 1962-1970, 3 folders (Box 3)
      - "A Theory of Adaptive Systems," 1960-1962 (Box 3)
      - "Language and Automata 1964-1970 (Box 12)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Atomic Energy Commission
    - Holland, John "The Study of Parallel, Iterative Computing Machines," 1961 (Box 3)
  - Department of Defense
    - Burks, Arthur "Proposal for Communications Science Research Program," 1961 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Department of health, Education and Welfare
    - Holland, John "A Theory of Adaptive Systems Based on Automata Theory," 1971 (Box 12)
  - Institute of Science and Technology (University of Michigan)
    - Burks, Arthur, "Theory of Adaptive Systems," 1960 (Box 3)
  - National Aeronautics and Space Administration
    - Holland, John, "Comparative Analyses of Genetic Algorithms in Relation to Other Multimodal Function Optimization Techniques 1974-1976 (Box 3)
    - Zeigler, Bernard, "Study of Genetic Direct Algorithms for Function Optimization 1971-1974, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - National Institute of Health
    - Burks, Arthur, "A Theory of Adaptive Systems," 1963-1972, 5 folders (Box 3)
    - Burks, Arthur "Computer Simulation in Biology...," 1971 (Box 12)
    - Holland, John "Computer Simulation In Biology: Theory and Practice," 1972-1977 (Box 3)
    - Holland, John "Formal Modeling and Computer Simulation," 1971 (Box 13)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - National Science Foundation
    - Burks, Arthur
      - "Chance, Cause, and Reason", 2-folders (Box 3)
      - "A Computer Simulation System Based on Cellular Automation Arrays," 1968-1971 (Box 3)
      - "Development of Graduate Instruction in Computer Science," 1969-1972 (Box 3)
      - "Formal and Interdisciplinary Studies of Adaptive and Computing Systems," 1979-1982 (Box 3)
      - "Formal Modeling and Computer Simulation," 1971-1974 (Box 3)
      - "Formal Theory of Multi-Dimensional, Nonlinear Systems, with Interdisciplinary Applications 1975-1980, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - "Graduate Instruction and Research in Computer and Communications Services," 1968-1971, 3 folders (Box 4)
      - "Interdisciplinary Applications of A Theory and Methodology of Modeling and Simulation," 19T6 (Box 4)
      - "Philosophical Implications of Computers and Computer Theory 1971 (Box 4)
      - "Structural Properties of Automata Computations," 1963-1966 (Box 4)
      - "The Study of Logical Design of Computer Nets," 1957 (Box 4)
      - "The Theory of Automata," 1959-1964, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Holland, John
      - "Experimental and Theoretical Studies of Adaptation and Fitness in an Isopod in Changing Environment," 1972-1973 (Box 4)
    - Hubbell, Stephen
      - "Experimental and Theoretical Studies of Adaptation and Fitness in an Isopod 1973 (Box 13)
    - Zeigler, Bernard
      - "Study of Genetic Direct Search Algorithms for Function Optimization," 1970-1973 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Navy
    - Burks, Arthur, "Logical Design Of Computer Nets," 1956-1967, 6 folders (Box 5)
    - Laing, Richard, "Machine Self Reference," 1976 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
  - Office of Naval Research
    - Burks, Arthur "Logical Design of Computer Automata," 1965-1969 (Box 13)
    - Burks, Arthur "Theory of Logical Design of Computer Nets," 1967 (Box 13)
  - Office of Ordinance Research: Miscellaneous
    - Office of Scientific Research: Miscellaneous (Box 5)
    - Project Michigan 1957-1961, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
- Papers and Reports
  The Papers and Reports files 5.5 linear feet) are arranged alphabetically by the last name of the author. They are primarily those that were generated by members of the LoCG as a result of grants received from and projects funded by the federal government. Together with the Grants and Proposals files, they document the areas of research in which the group concentrated, and the results achieved.
  - A (Box 5)
  - B
    - General, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Burks, 5 folders (Box 6)
  - C, 2 folders
    - folder 1 (Box 6)
    - folder 2 (Box 7)
  - E (Box 7)
  - F, 3 folders (Box 7)
  - G, 4 folders
    - folders 1-2 (Box 7)
    - folders 3-4 (Box 8)
  - H, 4 folders (Box 8)
  - J-K (Box 9)
  - L (Box 9)
  - Laing, Richard, 3 folders (Box 9)
  - Lundstrom, Stephen (Box 9)
  - M, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - P, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - R-S (Box 9)
  - T, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - W, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Z, 3 folders (Box 10)
  - Brender (Box 13)
  - Burks (Box 13)
  - Caricchio (Box 13)
  - Geller, 4 folders (Box 13)
  - Zeigler, 3 folders (Box 13)
- Burks, Arthur: Personal Files
  The Arthur Burks Personal files are arranged alphabetically by topic. Included are materials related to his work in the early 1950s as University of Michigan project leader for research done on the application of electronic computers to accounting problems. The research was contracted by the Burroughs Corporation. There are also materials from his service (both as member and as chairman) on the University Computer, Policy Committee, which was concerned with the requirements and utilization of university computer resources. There are interesting articles by Burks on the development of ENIAC, (the first electronic, digital, general-purpose scientific computer) with which he was associated, and there is a file containing background materials on the LoCG which provide an introduction to the history of the group.
  - Articles (includes history of ENIAC) (Box 10)
  - Association for Symbolic Logic 1958-1959 (administrative materials) (Box 10)
  - Burroughs Project 1950-1954
    - Contracts and Budgets (Box 10)
    - Correspondence
      - 1950-1951 (Box 10)
      - 1951-1952 (Box 10)
      - 1952-1954 (Box 10)
    - Monthly Reports (Box 11)
    - Personnel Hired (Box 11)
    - Project History (mostly bibliographies) (Box 11)
    - Project Plans (Box 11)
    - Reports Issued (Box 11)
  - Computer Policy Committee (University Committee on Computer Policy and Utilization)
    - 1965-1967 (Box 11)
    - 1968, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - 1969 (Box 11)
  - Computer Simulation System (Box 11)
  - Constructing vs. Instructing 1950 (memo to Burks from Frank Faulkner) (Box 11)
  - Correspondence
    - 1967 (includes earlier correspondence) (Box 11)
    - 1968 (Box 11)
  - Course Information 1966 (Box 11)
  - Engineering Summer Courses (Box 11)
  - Faculty/Researchers (administrative/personnel-type files)
    - Buchi, J.R. (Box 12)
    - Crichton, John Willison (Box 12)
    - Eggan, Lawrence C. (Box 12)
    - Elgot, Calvin C. (Box 12)
    - Finney, Alice E. (Box 12)
    - Tennenbaum, Stanley (Box 12)
    - Thatcher, James (Box 12)
    - Wang, Mao (Box 12)
    - Wilson, Dean (Box 12)
    - Wright, Jesse B. (Box 12)
  - Institute of Science and Technology 1959-1961 (administrative matters) (Box 12)
  - International Federation of Automatic Control 1962 (conference materials) (Box 12)
  - Logic of Computers Group
    - History/Background (Box 12)
    - Software/Hardware (Box 12)
  - Logical Design Lectures (given to Burroughs engineers, 1953) (Box 12)
  - Logical Design Lectures (given to Burroughs engineers, 1953) (Box 12)
  - Proposals (submitted by University of Michigan departments for review by Burks) (Box 12)
  - Rackham Grant 1962 (Box 12)
  - University of Michigan Computer Needs (correspondence and estimates) (Box 12)
  - von Neuman, John: Lectures (Box 12)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 12)
  - National Science Foundation Project Evaluations, 3 folders (Box 13)
  - Proposals 1963-1970 (Box 13)
  - Summer Conference 1962 (Box 13)
- Photographs
  The Photographs subgroup consists of five photos of an IBM 1800 computer being moved into the LoCG computer room
  - Photos of the IBM 1800 computer being moved into the Logic of Computers Group computer room, 5 items (Box 13)